Good morning everyone.
In our today's session we will be focusing on proximal lesions of the posterior teeth and we shall learn how to perform aesthetic restorations in these clinical manifestations of curious lesions using dental composites.
Despite significant improvements in composite systems and adhesive systems since their introduction, posterior restorations still require a careful placement technique in order to avoid micro leakage, post-operative sensitivity or less than ideal anatomy.
Marginal adaptation and micro leakage prevention is most critical at the gingival margin which is determined by the accident of lesion itself.
The formation of an adequate contact during the insertion of class 2 raisin composite can be particularly challenging as the lesion extends more gingivally.
In more superficial lesions such as this one, it's comparatively easier to manage because of its relationship with the incidental tissues.
Size of the lesion is directly related to the prognosis as a matrix adaptation is easier which can securely engage and provide optimum seal at the gingival floor.
As the lesion size increased and as it extends more gingivally, the more challenging the situation is.
As the preparation is enlarged, resistance form as well as bonding variables must be kept in mind during preparation, metricing and restoration.
Because whenever there is some kind of root involvement there will be some bonding issues because of less mineral content, maybe we are trying to bond on a cementum.
And the root dentine already has very less mineral content and higher collagen content so that's why there will be some bonding issues.
Next there will be some isolation problems because whenever there is a class two lesion depending on the size there are some inflamed papilla incidentally.
And these inflamed papilla produce exuded the inflammatory exit which can interfere with the etched or newly prepared surface.
Another variable is the depth of light penetration in these regions if the depth is greater there will be lesser chances of a proper light penetration and hence there will be less degree of conversion.
And because of less degree of conversion there could be some problems with the bonding or there could be some uncured composite.
There are chances of secondary lesion as well as post treatment hygiene maintenance problems because there are chances of overhanging in this region as well.
To build up the proximal wall and the insertion of class 2 composite restoration requires proper meta rising for a good contact formation, hence correct use of enamel and dentine etching bonding steps.
And incremental placement of the raisin composites and careful finishing is extremely important.
Anatomically correct and tight contacts are difficult to achieve with resin restorations because resin composite materials are not condensable like amalgam.
The use of amalgam matrix bands like flatmate for composite restorations generally leads to a straight point contact that are located in the occlusal third of the tooth which leads to under contouring of the situation.
As you can see in this illustration, if I'm using a flat matrix it is not going to create a contoured proximal contact, so hence we are getting a flat contact which is not ideal.
Remaining under contoured restoration will lead to overstimulation of the tissues.
The matrix systems for composite materials are designed to create curved proximal surfaces and tight contact areas.
These are generally comprised of thin contoured matrix bands and a tooth separator.
You can see that it is creating optimum contours in the proximal contact area, so after restoration it is producing an anatomical contact which is an ideal contact.
Talking about the indications, these are almost the same indications whenever doing a composite restoration in the posterior region.
Again small and moderate restorations preferably within enamel margin is advised.
Most premolars in molar restorations particularly when the aesthetics is in high demand.
A restoration that does not provide all the occlusal contacts is generally weaker.
And a restoration that does not have a higher occlusal contact or the patient is not suffering from any para functional habits.
A restoration that can appropriately isolate during the procedure, if you cannot perform adequate isolation there is a very bad prognosis of these kind of restorations.
Some restorations that may serve as foundations for crowns and some very large restorations that are used to strengthen the remaining or weakened structure.
When the operating site cannot be appropriately isolated I told you that these are among the contraindication.
Because if you will do the restoration there will be minimal curing in the gingival region, there are chances of bond failure in that region.
So it's always contraindicated that you use some other materials such as you can try a sandwich technique by using resin modified in these areas prior to use any composite.
Whenever there are some high occlusal forces because of pair functional habits this is among the contra indications.
Patients who are having high carry susceptibility and the patients who are with poor oral hygiene, the composites are contraindicated in these situations.
So again whenever we are talking about the advantages, aesthetics is the number one advantage.
Followed by we are not removing a lot of tooth structure as we are trying to do in amalgam which requires a strict geometry in order to get ideal retention and resistance form.
And with composites it is easier and less complex with preparation and since we are using bonding system it is providing insulation and the composite itself is an insulating material.
There is a decreased chance of micro leakage because of use of bonding adhesive system and we are also reinforcing remaining tooth structure by using composite and adhesive dentistry.
Among the disadvantages, if not used carefully there will be some polymerization shrinkage effects, some post op sensitivity or debonding if you have not followed all the recommendations during the preparation and etching and bonding process.
With some materials there is a low fracture toughness and it is quite a technique sensitive and time-consuming as compared to amalgam, and it is also expensive than amalgam so these are among the disadvantages.
So the problems with composites for use in class 2 restoration is number one, it's difficult to, it's not impossible but it is difficult to achieve moisture control.
But if you are using rubber dam you don't have to worry about that.
And in deep sub-gingival extension areas, adaptation of the matrix band and deep margin elevation and these are all difficult procedures to attempt for.
So next we'll discuss the clinical techniques for class 2 composite restorations.
As you know the shade of the tooth is the most important parameter when aesthetics is a paramount.
The shade of the tooth should be determined before the teeth are subjected to any prolonged drying because dehydrated teeth become lighter in shade as a result of decrease in translucency.
Minor or no tooth preparation, it may be necessary to clean the operating site with a slurry of pumice to remove the plaque pellicle and superficial stains along with the calculus deposits if there are.
Knowing the pre-op occlusal relationship is paramount for optimum restoration, so we shall mark the occlusal marks before any restorations.
Local anesthesia should be provided to make more pleasant and uninterrupted procedure, it also resulted in marked reduction in salivation.
Isolation is extremely important for a successful composite restoration, although with cotton rolls and other means of indirect isolation composite restoration can be performed but it's highly unpredictable.
In this pictorial you guys can see this wedge application in the teeth, each matrix band should be secured with a wedge.
A wedge is needed to maintain adaptation of the matrix to the tooth and the gingival margin to avoid the overhangs and prevent adjacent tooth from getting nicked with high speed handpiece.
Excessive wedging forces are unnecessary when an additional two separators such as rings will be used.
So inserted wedge where the embroidery is wide from buckle to lingual or from lingual to buckle.
Coming towards the benefits of the wedging are the pre-wedging will cause slight separation incidentally, it depresses the interdental papillae, it controls hemorrhage.
Prevent oozing of gravicular fluid, it seals the matrix gingivally and it also ensures the tight contacts.
Think before drill, so we'll coming towards the tooth preparation, wedging of the proximal contacts.
To prevent the adjacent tooth and to prevent the overhangs and the restorations, creating access to the faulty structure with your high speed handpiece.
Removal of the faulty structure, convenience form for the restoration and then the retention is obtained by the bonding.
Tooth preparation for class 2 has decreased pulpal depth of axial walls which allows greater conservation of tooth structure.
A closer and proximal wall converge occlusally and provide additional retention form from the vertical movements.
Proximal box preparation has a cable surface angle at right angle to the enamel surface facially or lingually.
Bevels are given on the occlusal surface and that are optimal due to the letter optional due to the direction of enamel rods whereas proximal surface beveling must be done prudently.
Gingival floors should clear the contact apically and they should be butt joint.